Finding aid for Newton Arvin papers MRBC.MS.00014
Mortimer Rare Book Collection
Newton Arvin papers
1913-63
Mortimer Rare Book Collection
Pierce, Charles R.
MRBC.MS.00014
18.5 linear feet (43 boxes)
Frederick Newton Arvin, Jr. was an English professor at Smith and one of the foremost literary biographers in American literature. He was elected to the board of directors of Yaddo—the writers' and artists' colony in Saratoga Springs, NY—in 1939. He received the National Book Award in 1951 for his Melville biography; in 1952 he was elected to the National Institute of Arts and Letters. Although Arvin was a brilliant scholar, his personal life was deeply troubled. He attempted suicide at least three times.Shame over his own homosexuality tormented him for his entire life, with the possible happy exception of his three-year relationship with Truman Capote, after which the two remained close friends. The Newton Arvin Papers are arranged in 12 series.
Scope and Contents
Conditions Governing Access
The Newton Arvin Papers are the physical property of the Mortimer Rare Book Room, Smith College.
The literary rights, including copyright of the correspondence, belongs to the authors of the letters or their legal representatives.
The copyrights associated with the materials gifted by Charles R. Pierce are retained by him. The transfer of these rights to The Trustees of Smith College will occur upon the death of Charles R. Pierce, or sooner if agreed to by him and Smith College.
The Newton Arvin Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Mortimer Rare Book Room, Smith College.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The letters of Newton Arvin (with a few exceptions) came to Smith College as designated in his will—"… accumulated correspondence to Smith College Library for selection and disposition at the discretion of the Librarian" following his death in 1963.
Arvin designated in his will that his niece, Barbara Pierce, was to have "…my diaries, journals, manuscripts whether published or unpublished, notes and the like which have not otherwise been otherwise disposed of by this will." In November 2011 Charles R. Pierce, the son of Barbara and Edward R. Pierce, gave this collection to Smith College. Not only did this gift contain the items as noted in the will, but the gift also contained some correspondence, photographs, documents related to the Arvin family and an unfinished biography by Arvin.
American literature--History and Criticism-Sources; English teachers-United States-Biography-Sources; Biographers -- United States -- Biography -- Sources; Pierce, Charles R.; Hawthorne, Nathaniel, 1804-1864 -- Biography; Arvin, Newton, 1900-1963.; Hawkins, John Baker; Melville, Herman, 1819-1892 -- Biography; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892 -- Biography; Yaddo (artists' colony)--History; Smith College. -- Faculty -- History -- Sources
- Correspondence to Newton Arvin, 1922-1960
- Correspondence from Newton Arvin, 1930-1962
- Third Part Correspondence, 1960-1874
- Diaries of Newton Arvin, 1913-1918; 1940-1963
- Journal and Commonplace Books of Newton Arvin, 1959-1962
- Books Read and to be Read by Newton Arvin, 1960-1969
- Newton Arvin's Notes and Partially Completed Manuscript of Autobiography/Memoirs, 1960-1969
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains Arvin's preliminary notes and the partially completed autobiography covering his family background and life to about 1915.
- Diary of John Baker Hawkins (1832-1911), 1865
  This series contains the diary of Newton Arvin's maternal grandfather for 1865, the year of the birth of Arvin's mother Jessie.
- Newton Arvin Family Photographs, 1770-1950
  This series contains family photographs (some unidentified) of the Arvin and Hawkins families, as well as various photographs of or by Newton Arvin.
- Memorabilia, Awards, Certificates and Articles by and about Newton Arvin, 1912-1960
- Research, Writings an d Teaching Papers of Newton Arvin, 1920-1960
  This series comprises the extensive notes that Arvin kept as a result of his reading, especially for his teaching and research. Included in this series is his manuscript (with corrections) of his biography on Longfellow. Arvin's habitually typed his detailed notes, often adding annotations by hand.
- Newton Arvin Miscellaneous Items, 1920-1960
  This series contains numerous items related to Valparaiso and Winona Lake, Indiana, an Amherst College thesis on the "Arvin affair at Smith College" and a copy of Joel Dorius's memoir.